Boker tov. Today's דף *daf* is סח *Samekh chet* 69 and we
have just read the משנה *Mishnah* at the beginning of this פרק
*perek*, so we pick up with the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* right afterwards.
The משנה *Mishnah* has talked about what the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol,
*Kohen Gadol* did now that all of the issues with the קטורת
*ketoret* is done and the blood of the פר *par* and the
שעיר *sa'ir* is done and the sending of the
שעיר לעזאזל *sa'ir la'azazel*, even getting the carcasses of the other two
animals, sending them to be burnt, so all of that stuff is
done and now he comes to do a reading of the תורה
Torah *Torah*, makes ברכות Berakhot. *berakhot* afterwards about the עבודה avoda. *avodah*,
about the atoning of sin, about ישראל *Yisrael*, and about the כהנים
Kohanim *kohanim*,
and this is what he's doing while those carcasses of those animals
are being burnt outside of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash? *Beit Hamikdash*.
He does this either in his same בגדי לבן *bigdei lavan*, the
same clothes of the כהן kohen *kohen*, or in a special cloak,
a personal cloak that he can make for himself. Now before we
begin the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, I wanted to say, which we did
not get a chance to discuss yesterday, the important question, why is
he doing this reading of the תורה Torah *Torah*? What function is
it? I mean okay, it's very nice, like we know okay, one
of the things you do during services is you have a reading
of the תורה Torah *Torah*, but why are they doing it here?
Obviously you could say that it's exactly that, it's to show you
how to connect the עבודה avoda *avodah* that's being done and show
to the source in the תורה Torah *Torah* where it's coming from,
to connect it to that. But it's interesting to look at two
sources that are given for why he's reading the תורה Torah *Torah*.
So if you take a look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, בא לקרא
*Ba Likro*, the first רש"י Rashi *Rashi* on the משנה *Mishnah*, רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says, את הפרשה וילפינן ממלואים דאמרינן פרק קמא מניין שאף
מקרא פרשה מעכב וזה הדבר אשר צוה ה' *Es haparsha, vyalfinan mimiluim
d'amrinan perek kama menayin she'af mikra parsha me'akev v'zeh hadavar asher tzivah
Hashem*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* way back on דף ה *Daf
Heh*, way way back in the first פרק *perek*, said that by
the מלואים *miluim*, according to one opinion, because it says זה הדבר
אשר צוה ה' *Zeh hadavar asher tzivah Hashem*, that משה *Moshe* actually
had to sort of say over the פסוקים Pesukim *psukim*, I don't
know if they were פסוקים *psukim* yet, say over what God had
said to him
before or while during the doing of the מלואים *miluim*. He had
to make that declaration and even reading over that פרשה *parsha* was
a necessary part of the מלואים *miluim*. Now that was the period
if you remember leading up to
the dedication and here we use the מלואים *miluim* before as a
model for the seven days leading up to יום כיפור Yom Kippur,
*Yom Kippur*, but רש"י Rashi *Rashi* is saying and we'll see in
a minute the ירושלמי Yerushalmi? *Yerushalmi* that that actually is learned from
there that this type of a special service and there is a
similar sense, right, we've been talking so much about the blood and
the blood as cleansing and by the מלואים *miluim* it wasn't just
preparing the כהנים Kohanim, *kohanim*, it was preparing the מקדש Mikdash. *mikdash*,
cleansing, sanctifying the מקדש Mikdash *mikdash*, and learning from there the importance
of the reading of the פרשה *parsha* to show how this is
sort of based on the biblical verses that this is from God.
This is what רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says. If we take a look
at, I'm sorry, whoops, dropped it.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry. Where is the רש"י *Rashi* they did the
קריאת התורה krias hatorah *kriyat hatorah* based on מלואים *miluim*. Again מלואים
*miluim* was we normally learn the seven days leading up to יום
כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*, but here again by the same way
מלואים *miluim* was also sanctifying the כהנים Kohanim. *kohanim* and the מקדש
Mikdash. *mikdash*, and here too the whole thing of the blood is
cleansing and sanctifying, cleansing the מקדש Mikdash, *mikdash*. It's interesting now that
we're using the מלואים *miluim* for that model and the same way
you need the קריאה *kriah* there you need one here. If you
take a look at the תוספות ישנים Tosafot Yeshanim, *Tosfos Yeshanim* he
gives a very different alternate explanation.
It's at the bottom of the page here again in the microscopic
print, second column, middle of the column, בא לו כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol לקרא *Ba lo Kohen Gadol likro*. He says הכא הואיל והפסיק
עבודת היום וגמר עשיית עיקר עבודות כפרה *Hacha ho'il vehifsik avodas hayom
v'gamar asiyat ikar avodos kapara*. So basically right, he's at a closure
moment here. He's done the basic עבודה avoda. *avodah*, right, the only
thing really left is the removing of the כף *kaph*, but he's
basically done the major עבודה avoda, *avodah* of the יום *yom*. So
right, everything is done. So יש לו לקרוא ולברך על המחילה ועל
סדר הברכות *Yesh lo likro ulevarech al hamachila v'al seder haberachos*. Okay
so basically he says a shocking thing. It's not primarily about the
קריאת התורה *kriyat hatorah* or it is about making the ברכות Berakhot.
*berakhot* afterwards. It's afterwards, it's saying accept the עבודה avoda *avodah*, atone
for the sin, מוחל לעוונותינו *moichel la'avonoseinu*, bless the מקדש Mikdash *mikdash*.
So all of these things is to give a to give the
blessings about now this is the center, this is of the day.
So you don't want it to just be through the ritual, you
want also through the words, ברכות *berakhot*, תפילה *tefillah* to give meaning
and to use this as the opportunity to actually. say the תפילות
*tefillot* of the יום *yom* and to frame the עבודה avodah? *avodah*.
So again, fascinating because of this transition
between מקדש Mikdash, *mikdash* and our reality of תפילה *tefillah*, right, understanding
that the purpose here of the קריאת התורה *krias hatorah*, you know,
is it sounds like it's a lot to allow meaning
a שול shul, *shul* in the middle.
Exactly, is creating a שול shul *shul* and you have the whole
חזן הכנסת chazzan haknesses, *chazzan haknesset*, you have the whole חזן chazzan,
הכנסת *chazzan haknesset*. So creating, is grafting that reality, I don't know
if I said that much, but you're right, it's the חזן chazzan
הכנסת *chazzan haknesset* and ראש Rosh הכנסת *rosh haknesset*, grafting that reality
onto the מקדש Mikdash, *mikdash* and allowing it to frame or to
be a closure for the rituals. Now, the קריאה *kriya* could also,
it's not just the ברכות *brachot*, the קריאה *kriya* could also be,
like I say, connecting it back to the פסוקים *psukim*, but he
seems to really underscore the opportunity for the ברכות *brachot*. And then
he quotes the ירושלמי Yerushalmi, *yerushalmi* which is more or less רש"י
*rashi*. ירושלמי מניין לקרוא הפרשה *Yerushalmi minayin likros haparsha* רבי rebbe? אידי
בשם רבי rebbe? יוחנן *Rabbi Idi b'shem Rabbi Yochanan* ויעש מה תלמוד
לומר כאשר צוה ה' *vayaas mah talmud lomar kaasher tziva Hashem* מכאן
לקריאת הפרשה *mikan likrias haparsha*, again going back to the מילואים *miluim*.
But according to him, it's quite fascinating that the major purpose of
this is for the, what do you call it, for, to allow
for the ברכות *brachot*. Okay, let's take a look now at the
גמרא Gemara *gemara*. מדקתני באצטלי לבן *midtani b'istali lavan*, since it says
משלו *m'shelo* that if he wants to, he can use his own
white tunic, as opposed to continuing to wear the בגדי לבן *bigdei
lavan*, מכלל דקריאה לאו עבודה avoda היא *michlal d'kriya lav avodah hi*.
So it seems obviously the reading is not an עבודה avoda *avodah*
per se. I mean, it's not, you know, it's not in the
פסוקים *psukim*, so, but anyway, you could have just proven it from
there, why go into what we just discussed, where does it come
from, but clearly anyway, the fact that it doesn't need בגדי כהונה
bigdei kehuna? *bigdei kehuna* proves it's not an עבודה avoda. *avodah*. ותני
אם רצה לקרוא בבגדי בוץ קורא *vetani im ratza likros b'bigdei butz
korei*, but it also says he can be wearing the בגדי כהונה
bigdei kehuna *bigdei kehuna*. So now we have an interesting phenomenon, something
that is not an עבודה avoda *avodah*, you can be wearing the
בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna *bigdei kehuna* for it. שמע מינה בגדי כהונה
ניתנו ליהנות shma mina bigdei kehuna nitnu l'hanos. בהן *shma mina bigdei
kehuna nitnu lehenas bahen*? Can we infer from this that you are
allowed to derive benefit from the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna. *bigdei kehuna*,
meaning at least minimally wear it during a period, during something which
is not part of the עבודת המקדש *avodat hamikdash*, which means you
derive some benefit, it's clothing you, it's warming you, you know, you're
getting benefits from wearing them and it's not part of the עבודה
*avodah* itself. Can that tell you that? So the גמרא Gemara *gemara*
says no, דילמה שאני קריאה דצורך עבודה היא *dilma shani kriya d'tzorech
avodah hi*. Maybe קריאת התורה *krias hatorah* is different because קריאת התורה
*krias hatorah* is for the sake of, is for the sake of
the עבודה *avodah*. Like we just said, you know, either according to
רש"י *rashi*, because it's learned from the פסוקים *psukim*, that it's a
necessary part. Again, I don't think it would be מעכב *meakev*, although
רש"י *rashi* does quote an earlier גמרא Gemara *gemara* by מעכב *meakev*
by the מילואים *miluim*, nobody ever said this is מעכב *meakev*. It's
not necessarily בגדי לבן *bigdei lavan*. But anyway, something that's learned out
that it's part of the עבודת היום *avodat hayom*, or תוספות ישנים
Tosafot Yeshanim *tosafot yeshanim*, even if it's not based on פסוקים *psukim*,
but it's to give framing, to give meaning, it's all connected to
the עבודת היום *avodat hayom*. It does not, you cannot infer from
this that a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *kohen gadol*, a כהן Kohen
*kohen* can wear בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna, *bigdei kehuna* when it's not
connected to the עבודה *avodah*. So let's take a look. גמרא Gemara.
*gemara* says דאיבעיא לן *d'ibaya lan*, because this really connects to a
long-standing question we've had. And we have a question: בגדי כהונה bigdei
kehuna ניתנו ליהנות בהן או לא ניתנו ליהנות בהן *bigdei kehuna nitnu
lehenas bahen o lo nitnu lehenas bahen*? Can a כהן Kohen. *kohen*
derive benefit from the בגדי כהונה Bigdei Kehuna *bigdei kehuna*? Can he
wear them not during a period of the עבודה *avodah* or not?
תא שמע tashma, *ta shma*, come and hear. לא היו ישנים בבגדי
קודש kodesh? *lo hayu yeshenim b'bigdei kodesh*. So they wouldn't sleep in
their בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah *bigdei kehuna*. So גמרא Gemara *gemara* says,
okay, שינה sheina דלא *sheina de-lo*. They wouldn't sleep because then you'd
be passing gas and that obviously would not be appropriate. But הא
מיכל אכלי *ha-michal achli*, but
presumably they could be eating while they were wearing the בגדי כהונה
bigdei kehunah. *bigdei kehuna*, just sleeping they can't do. No, eating you
can't prove anything from. דילמה שאני אכילה דצורך עבודה היא *dilma shani
achila d'tzorech avodah hi*. Eating, at least eating of קרבנות korbanot *korbanot*,
is also צורך עבודה *tzorech avodah*. Is part of the עבודה *avodah*.
כדתניא *kid'tanya*, like we taught in a ברייתא Braisa. *baraita*: ואכלו אתם
אשר כפר בהם *ve'achlu otam asher kupar bahem*. So they shall eat
them, those that are atoned by them. ללמד *l'lamed*, so the linking
of eating with atonement, שהכהנים אוכלים ובעלים מתכפרים *shehakohanim ochlim u-be'alim mitkaprim*.
The eating of the כהנים Kohanim *kohanim* is part of the כפרה
*kappara* of the owners. The eating of the כהנים *kohanim* in other
places is connected to the eating, the consumption of the מזבח *mizbe'ach*.
Again, another point, seeing the כהנים *kohanim* as type of a כלי
קודש *klei kodesh*, type of a כלי המקדש *klei hamikdash*. Their consumption
of the meat when they eat the meat of certain קרבנות *korbanot*,
mostly it would be a חטאת *chatas*, their consumption of the meat
is like the eating that's done on the altar. So the עולה
*olah* is burnt fully, the חטאת *chatas*, the innards are burnt, and
the meat is eaten, not by the owners but by the כהנים
*kohanim*. Okay, so therefore it's part of the atonement, so just because
you wear בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah *bigdei kehuna* for that doesn't prove
a more general point. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says fine, but
it's still there's a lot of things other than sleeping that it's
implicitly allowing, not just eating. So we're going to try again. So
the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says fine, שינה הוא דלא *sheina hu d'lo*.
Let's try again. But okay, all it says is you can't sleep
in it. הא הלוכי מהלכי *ha-haluchei m'halchi*. But you can walk around
in them. You know, you don't have to strip them off the
moment the day is over, keep them on a little bit, walk
around in them. Okay, so בדין הוא *bedin hu*, so you see
again you can derive benefit, meaning you're not limited to using them
only during the time of the עבודה *avodah*. So גמרא Gemara *gemara*
says בדין הוא דהלוכי נמי לא *bedin hu d'hiluchei nami lo*. You
know what? Really, you can't even walk around in them. You have
to strip them off as soon as you're done with the עבודה.
וסיפא איצטריכא ליה, v'seifa itztrichtei, we need this for, we need the
idea that it says don't wear them while you're sleeping, not to
tell me you can wear them all other times, but to emphasize
the last line: פושטן ומקפלן ומניחן תחת ראשיהן, poshtan u'mkaflan u'manichan tachas
rasheihen, that you can fold them up after you—when you're going to
go to sleep and use them as a pillow. So the חידוש,
chiddush, it's not to imply don't sleep yes do anything else, it's
telling you don't sleep but here's the חידוש. chiddush. And maybe don't
do other things, don't walk around in them. But here's the חידוש:
chiddush: you can use it as a pillow. Now, of course, as
soon as you say that, it's like, okay, that's that's also הנאה.
hana'ah. So what do you mean? You can't walk around in them
but you can use them as a pillow? So let's talk about
that. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to turn to that.
Okay, פושטן ומקפלן ומניחן תחת ראשיהן, poshtan u'mkaflan u'manichan tachas rasheihen, take
them off and fold them and put under your head. So the
גמרא Gemara says fine, שמע מינה Shema mina. בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah
ניתנו ליהנות. So you see you can derive benefit, you can use
them as a pillow. So אמר רב פפא לא תימא תחת ראשיהן
אלא אימא כנגד ראשיהן. amar Rav Pappa lo teima tachas rasheihen ela
eima k'neged rasheihen. So that's a lot to get out of this
proof. You know, it says don't sleep but use it as a
pillow, and what we're saying is: don't sleep in it, don't do
anything in it, don't walk around in them, don't use it as
a pillow, but you can fold it up and leave it near
your head. So why, what's the חידוש? chiddush? Of course you could
leave it near your head. So the question would be that, you
know, either concern that if we let you leave it near your
head, that'll lead to you sleeping in it or sleep on it,
you know, and that would be the problem. Or רש"י also says
you would roll over on it and forget the איסור הנאה, issur
hana'ah, just would not be respectful for it. So that's the חידוש.
chiddush. But maybe you can't really do anything, not you know. And
the only point here is that there's nothing you could do, but
you can put it near your head. Of course, again, the language
is very misleading if that's what it's saying. So the גמרא Gemara
says, but within this approach, אמר רב משרשיא שמע מינה, amar Rav
Mesharshiya shma mina, you can infer from this if we read it
that you're allowed to be near your head, תפילין מן הצד שפיר
דמי, tefillin min hatzad shapir dami, that you can actually wrap up
your תפילין tefillin and put them near your head when you go
to sleep. Maybe you want to keep them close and protect them.
And again, we're not afraid that you'll roll over on them and
that won't be respectful for the תפילין. tefillin. So that is, if
you know, an interesting
comparison because as I said
before, why is שינה particularly problematic with בגדי כהונה? bigdei kehunah So
what I said, you know, what רש"י and others say is a
concern of passing gas while you're asleep. That is something we are
familiar with with the concern that חז"ל Chazal have about תפילין tefillin
and why not to put תפילין tefillin on at night because you'll
fall asleep and then you'll pass gas. So it's—and here the גמרא
Gemara, makes that comparison explicitly. If you can put the בגדי כהונה
bigdei kehunah near your head, you can put the תפילין tefillin near
your head. And that is interesting because you know, according to some,
having the—תפילין tefillin is also compared to like the ציץ, tzitz, the
תפילין של ראש, tefillin shel rosh, the ציץ tzitz of the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, the thing on the head. And thinking about—and this
is a longer conversation—but other places in חז"ל Chazal where these two
religious garments, ציצית tzitzit and תפילין, tefillin, in some ways subtly, in
some ways less subtly, are seen as a type of a בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehunah for laypeople out in the real world. You know,
it's something that you wear and frames your consciousness of God and
your activity in the world as a type of an עבודה. I
think I mentioned once before, you know, that the רא"ש says the
reason we do נטילת ידיים netilat yadayim in the morning is like
the כהנים wash their hands before their עבודה in the מקדש. Mikdash.
We wash our hands before our עבודת השם avodat Hashem that is
going to take place in the larger world. So it's interesting here
the comparison of this to בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehunah, Yes, question...
so passing gas is considered just a—but according to those who say
to pass gas you should take them off?
Yeah, that's an interesting question. I hadn't thought about that. That's right.
You're right. You know, the same way you take off your תפילין.
tefillin. Yeah, I don't know. It's a good question. רש"י is the
one that mentions that, but I'd have to—I don't recall that ever
being discussed. Oh my god, a כהן Kohen has to pass gas,
wait, I
gotta run, take off my בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, come back.
But okay, it's a good question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. So related to the notion of גוף נקי. guf naki.
Yeah, yeah. So, internally נקי. naki. Exactly. So, so we still haven't
proven whether you can wear the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna. when you're
not doing the עבודה. Certainly the simple sense of all of this
is that you can, but the גמרא Gemara is saying a way
of getting out of it. Now, before we go on with the
proofs, I should mention a moment about why would you be allowed
to? Haven't they been sanctified? Haven't they—aren't they קודש? Why would you
be allowed to wear them otherwise? Isn't there מעילה me'ilah concern? So
some ראשונים Rishonim bring down the idea of like, as you might
remember from שקלים, Shekalim, לב בית דין מתנה עליהם, lev beis din
masneh aleihem, which basically means, you know, if we're creating a communal
sanctity, we can set up all of the conditions. We can somehow
stipulate: it applies here and it doesn't apply here, which is pretty
funny, like the קדושה kedusha that turns on and off at different
times. Another explanation, which seems to be a more satisfying one in
the תוספות ישנים, Tosafot Yeshanim is: look, you know, לא ניתנה תורה
למלאכי השרת. lo nitna Torah l'malachei hashareis. If you were not allowed
to get benefit when you're not doing the עבודה, it means the
split second the עבודה is done, you have to strip them. That's
not humanly possible. And once it's not humanly possible and you have
to assume that the תורה Torah, gives you a certain amount of
latitude. then what it means is that as soon as that's true,
it's not 100 percent limited to God use. And if you remember
by מעילה, Me'ila, the idea is קדשי השם. Kadshei Hashem. It has
to be 100 percent, like even a שלמים Shlamim is not מעילה.
Me'ila. So once it's not 100 percent limited and once you already
have a little bit of latitude, then it's out of the category
of מעילה. Me'ila. Although interestingly, the question is how much latitude are
we giving. If you say ניתנו ליהנות בהם, Nitnu Leihanot Bahem, can
I wear them during outside of the בית המקדש? Beit Hamikdash. Can
I wear them on the weekday? Okay, can I take them home
with me? Or maybe only a type of a reasonable latitude in
the sense of wearing them while you're in the מקדש Mikdash, or
while you know or in the environs of the מקדש. Mikdash. How
much latitude are we actually giving? All right, so those are some
questions to be thinking about. Let's continue now in the גמרא. Gemara
Okay. The גמרא Gemara says הכא נמי מסתבר דכנגד ראשיהם. Hacha nami
mistabra dekneged rasheihem. You know what? It makes sense to think that
it's only near their head and not under their head. דאי סלקא
דעתך תחת ראשיהם, De'i salka da'atach tachas rasheihem, if it's under their
head, ותיפוק ליה משום כלאים? Visipok lei mishum kilayim? How about the
problem that one of the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna of the of
a normal כהן Kohen is made with שעטנז? Shatnez? The אבנט Avnet
is made with with שעטנז, Shatnez, with wool and linen. So so
how can you therefore how could you be sleeping on it as
a pillow? Wouldn't that be the using of שעטנז? Shatnez? Now it's
not wearing of שעטנז, Shatnez, but that's what we're so that's what
we're about to discuss. So let's take a look. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. דהא איכא אבנט. Deha ika avnet. There's
the belt. ואי אמרת דניתנו ליהנות בהם, Vei amrat denitnu leihanot bahem,
even if there's no קדושה Kedusha problem, קא מיתהני מכלאים. Ka mis'hanei
mikilayim. You're benefiting from כלאים. Kilayim. Now we never I never heard
that שעטנז Shatnez was אסור בהנאה, Assur BeHana'a, so we'll discuss that
in a minute. But that's the גמרא's Gemara concern. It's שעטנז. Shatnez.
If you really are using it for a pillow. Wait one minute.
Wait one minute. הניחא למאן דאמר אבנטו של כהן גדול זהו אבנטו
של כהן הדיוט. Hani'acha leman de'amar avneto shel Kohen Gadol zehu avneto
shel Kohen Hedyot. If you say the the belt of the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol. on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur. which is all linen,
is the same of the belt as the כהן הדיוט. Kohen Hedyot.
So the כהן הדיוט Kohen Hedyot would wear a linen belt. So
then that's fine because then the כהן הדיוט's Kohen Hedyot בגדים Begadim
does not have שעטנז. Shatnez. אלא למאן דאמר אבנטו של כהן גדול
לא זהו אבנטו של כהן הדיוט. Ella leman de'amar avneto shel Kohen
Gadol lo zehu avneto shel Kohen Hedyot. The linen belt of the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol, is not the same as the normal belt
of a כהן. The normal belt of a כהן is שעטנז. Shatnez.
So then if that's true that the normal belt of a כהן
is שעטנז, Shatnez, מאי איכא למימר? Mai ika lemeimar? How can you
be sleeping on it? Aren't you aren't you basically sleeping on שעטנז?
Shatnez? So it must be it doesn't mean on it, it must
be near it. Now of course what you could say is so
you don't have the belt in the pile, you have the rest
of the clothes in the pile that you're using for a pillow.
But the גמרא Gemara assumes it means everything including the belt. So
so obviously it means near it and not on it or else
you'd have a שעטנז Shatnez problem. Now the גמרא Gemara says וכי
תימא, Vechi teima, maybe you want to say כלאים בלבישה הוא דאסור,
Kilayim belvisha hu de'assur, בהעלאה שרי, Beha'ala shari, which is exactly what
I would have said. The תורה Torah doesn't say don't get benefit
from שעטנז. Shatnez. It says לא יעלה עליך, Lo ya'aleh alecha, don't
put it on you. לא תלבש, Lo silbash, don't wear it. So
wearing שעטנז, Shatnez, having it on you, maybe having a blanket of
שעטנז Shatnez on you, over you, is a problem. But a pillow
is neither being worn nor on top of you. So since when
is that a שעטנז Shatnez problem? So the גמרא Gemara says והתניא,
Vehatanya, okay, that's a good point. But
here we taught a ברייתא. braita.
לא יעלה עליך, Lo ya'aleh alecha, don't put it on you, שעטנז,
Shatnez, אבל אתה מותר
להציעו תחתיך.
Aval
ata mutar lehatzi'o tachtecha.
You actually can lay
it underneath
you. You can have it as a blanket, as a sheet to
lie
on. It's not wearing and it's not
on.
אבל אמרו חכמים, Aval amru Chachamim, although that's biblically true, the sages
said אסור לעשות כן, Assur la'asos kein, you're not allowed to do
this, שמא תכרך נימא אחת על בשרו, Shema ticharech nima achas al
besaro, lest a little loose
strand of שעטנז Shatnez from the blanket goes over your lying there,
and you know, and on a blanket of שעטנז Shatnez and a
little string goes over your pinky, so
then that is לא יעלה עליך, Lo ya'aleh alecha, it's going on
you.
Okay. Did you hear that? What? I wasn't trying to get it
on? All right, so you could say exactly אונס Ones or whatever,
אינו מתכוין, Eino miskaven, is it a פסיק רישא Psik reisha or
not. But חז״ל Chazal did not want it to happen even inadvertently.
It's a good point. Often אינו מתכוין Eino miskaven is something we're
not worried about. And therefore rabbinically it's forbidden and we're assuming that
the same rabbinic restriction would apply to the כהנים, right? So you
could say, well maybe not, maybe we give special latitude to the
כהנים. So again, how could it be saying it obviously can't mean
literally use it as a pillow? It would be a שעטנז Shatnez
concern even though not a biblical one but rabbinically you shouldn't be
sleeping on שעטנז. Shatnez. So that shows that we don't mean we
don't mean use it as a pillow. We mean have it near
your head. Who would want to be sleeping on a belt? It
doesn't seem too comfortable. No, it's a linen belt. It's all cloth.
It's it's all the same material. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says
והתניא, Vehatanya, I'm sorry, we just read that. וכי תימא דמפסיק ליה
מידי ביני ביני, Vechi teima demafsik lei midi beini beini, you'll say
ah, so what you know what you'll do? You'll have the belt
will be will be at the bottom and you won't have your
head directly on the belt. So a little string from the belt
is not going to go on you. That's not going to be
a solution for this rabbinic problem. ואמר רבי שמעון בן פבי אמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי אמר רבי משום קהלא קדישא שבירושלים. Ve'amar Rabbi
Shimon ben Pabi amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi amar Rabbi mishum kahala
kadisha shebeYerushalayim. So this tradition in the name of the holy community
of Jerusalem... That's very interesting, there it does occur sometimes in the
גמרא, Gemara I don't know who that is. אפילו עשר מצעות זו
על גב זו, Afilu eser matzaot zo al gav zo, but the
princess and the pea, even if you've got ten blankets or pillows
one on top of the other and the כלאים kilayim and the
שעטנז shatnez is the bottom one, the rabbinic restriction still applies once
we said don't sleep on it, even if you do it in
a way that it won't come in contact with your body, we
rabbinically categorically said don't do it. So therefore, and presumably the כהנים
have the same restriction, and therefore it can't mean use it as
a pillow, it must mean אלא לאו שמע מינה כנגד ראשיהן. ela
lav shema mina keneged rosheihen. It must mean near their head, not
under their head. שמע מינה. shema mina The גמרא takes that as
good evidence. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, but even it's quite
fascinating, שמע מינה shma mina. usually ends the discussion, but the גמרא
is not done. I'm sorry, so was this whole עשר מצעות זו
על גב זו, eser matzaot zo al gav zo, does it have
nothing to do with כהונה? kehunah? This is just a separate... Right,
rabbinically now moved away from this maybe, maybe a strand from the
בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna, will go over you, right? No, no, we
see this all as part of the rabbinic restriction. Don't lie on
it even with ten separations. We have categorically rabbinically prohibited it even
when it is not possible that it will lead to this thing.
Once we had disallowed it, we disallowed it. רב אשי אמר, Rav
Ashi amar, לעולם תחת ראשיהן. le'olam tachat rosheihen. רב אשי Rav Ashi
says no, no, going back, it means use it as a pillow,
it is a proof that you can get benefit from בגדי כהונה.
bigdei kehuna. What about the שעטנז shatnez concern? והא קא מתהני מכלאים,
veha ka mit-hani mikilayim, again, a funny phrase, you're benefiting from כלאים,
kilayim, but bottom line it means rabbinically at least we've proved you
can't sleep on it. So he says no, בגדי כהונה קשים הם.
bigdei kehunah kashim hem. No, they are sort of like Michael said,
it's not so comfortable. It's a stiff material. And since it's a
stiff material, we are not concerned rabbinically that a little strand will
come on your body because it's just very stiff. It doesn't have
like loose strands. Okay, so we don't have the rabbinic concern. So
once you're dealing with a type of a material that could go
on you, like a soft blanket that there could be a loose
strand, that's categorically forbidden, even if it's under ten other blankets. But
if you're dealing with a type of material that it's not possible,
a very stiff material, then we won't have the rabbinic restriction. Okay,
so the rabbinic restriction is categorical once it's a type of a
garment that could be a problem, but if it's a type of
a garment that will never be a problem, then it's okay. כי
הא דאמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Ki ha d'amar Rav Huna
brei d'Rav Yehoshua, as רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע Rav Huna brei
d'Rav Yehoshua said, האי נמטא גמדא דנרש, hai namta gamda de-Narsh, this
like hard felt that comes from the place of נרש, Narsh, right,
felt, you know, felt like felt, שריא sharya is permissible, you can
sleep on it because we're not afraid that it's hard and it's
whatever felt, we're not afraid of a loose strand. Okay, so he
says there are times where we do not have the rabbinic restriction.
I should mention the way I just read it is following תוספות.
Tosafot. רש"י says something even more radical. רש"י says that even if
you wear a garment made out of a hard cloth so it
doesn't really like mold to your body and doesn't really provide warmth
to your body, so that is not real wearing and that's not
even a biblical restriction. Okay, that's pretty radical, but the simple explanation
is if it's a hard stiff garment then it is not a
concern of this rabbinic concern and therefore it could mean under the
head. Now, so insofar as we haven't really proven whether you could
wear בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna not in the immediate context, we have
a clear... it certainly seems to be it's only a sleeping problem,
it could be under your head other times, we've got out of
it. I do want to make also one other quick point, which
is as תוספות ישנים asks, why did the גמרא only here raise
שעטנז? shatnez? Any discussion of wearing בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna, at other
times, like walking around with it, shouldn't the גמרא be raising שעטנז
shatnez concerns? Right, think about it. Any time you're asking can you
wear בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna, at other times, unless you're talking about
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol. if we've now said that the belt
is שעטנז, shatnez, so how could you walk around with the בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehuna when you're done with the עבודה? Forget, what about
the שעטנז shatnez concerns? Ask it back there. So he actually says,
you know, that no, it could be, and this is a fascinating
idea, once שעטנז shatnez is allowed in a certain category, is it
given like a blanket allowance? A הותרה hutra essentially. There's a famous
position of רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam that you know, if you make,
if you have a linen garment, the wool, the blue, the blue
string halakhically has to be wool, so that's an allowance of שעטנז
shatnez because there's no other way to do the מצוה mitzvah of
the blue. So you have that. Can you keep on wearing that
garment at night? Because at night you're not fulfilling the מצוה. mitzvah.
And רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says yes, once the תורה Torah? allowed
שעטנז shatnez in this garment, even when you're not doing the מצוה,
mitzvah, you're allowed to continue wearing it. So in a similar way,
as long as I'm wearing בגדי כהונה and wearing it in the
מקדש, Mikdash let's say, not at home, that's similar to רבינו תם'ס
Rabbeinu Tam's point, the תורה Torah. has completely allowed שעטנז. shatnez. The
only concern the גמרא had about שעטנז shatnez was when you strip
it and you want to use it as a pillow. But as
long as you're wearing it and that sort of Torah allowed it
as a garment to be worn, then it's blanket allowance. It's quite
fascinating to realize the גמרא did not raise the... only raises the
שעטנז shatnez in the pillow context, not in the general question of
how can we talk about you wearing your בגדי כהונה, what about
the שעטנז shatnez problem? Yes, good questions for Monday. Does רש״י Rashi
know the ירושלמי? Sometimes רש״י Rashi quotes ירושלמי, yes. And also I've
seen this סברא, sevara, you can't take this for למדות lomdus literally,
I've seen it in other places of a ביני ביני. beini beini.
Where's ביני ביני? beini beini? ביני ביני beini beini just means between
the two of them. ביניהם. beineihem. Yeah, no, between the two of
what? That's... Between you and the bottom and the actual שעטנז. shatnez.
Oh, the 10 fingers. Okay. So, okay. So, okay. גמרא says תא
שמע, come in here. בגדי כהונה, so we're still asking this question.
היוצא בהם למדינה אסור. hayotzei bahem lamedina asur. You can't wear them
in the מדינה, medina, which means anywhere outside of the מקדש Mikdash
for this context. ובמקדש, uvemikdash, and in the מקדש, Mikdash בין בשעת
עבודה בין שלא בשעת עבודה מותר, bein besha'at avoda bein shelo besha'at
avoda mutar, but you whether it's when you're doing the עבודה or
not doing the עבודה is permissible מפני שבגדי כהונה ניתנו ליהנות בהם.
mipnei shebigdei kehuna nitnu leihanot bahem. Okay, that's a pretty explicit ברייתא.
braita, Cause you can wear them when you're not doing the עבודה.
So שמע מינה. That is a good proof. Okay. Now then the
question is why not wear them in the מדינה? medina? So רש״י
Rashi says once yes we are saying tech- it's not a קדושה
kedusha problem, but רש״י Rashi says שנוהג בהם חול. shenoheg bahem chol.
Once you're wearing it out of the מקדש, Mikdash that is not
respectful of the בגדי כהונה. Right? Again, you could also have speculated
like I said before that if the reason you're allowed to wear
the בגדי כהונה not at the time of the עבודה is because
like לא ניתנה תורה למלאכי השרת, lo nitna Torah lemalachei hasharet, right?
That it's impossible to strip at the minute off, so clearly you
have some allowance. But it's possible that that allowance is only in
the context of as long as you're still in the מקדש. Mikdash,
Right? So it's not just a problem that it's not respectful. Maybe
exactly this idea of the קדושה kedusha and so on will give
you a latitude when you're in the מקדש, Mikdash but it does
not extend to outside of the מקדש. Mikdash Okay. So anyway, but
that is what we have. We have a very clear proof of
this. So now let's see as the גמרא continues. שמע ובמדינה לא?
shma uvemedina lo? Are you telling me you can't wear them outside?
ובמדינה לא? uvemedina lo? והא, veha, where are we? ותניא, vatanya, on
a ברייתא, Baraita בעשרים וחמישה בטבת, be'esrim vechamisha betevet, on the 25th
of Tevet. This is- this is basically like the מגילת תענית, Megillat
Ta'anit, days that are, you know, days that are forbidden to fast
because of special things that happened primarily in the מקדש Mikdash period.
So on the 25th of Tevet, יום הר גריזים הוא, yom Har
Gerizim hu, it is the day of Mount Gerizim. דלא למספד, delo
lemispad, you can't have a- you can't have a הספד, hesped, a
eulogy, and fast, יום שביקשו כותים את בית אלוהינו, yom shebikshu kutim
et beit elokeinu, the day the Samaritans, whose their home base was
הר גריזים, Har Gerizim, they were trying to destroy the מקדש Mikdash
from מאלכסנדרוס מוקדון, Me'alexandros mokdon, from Alexander of Macedonia. From Alexander, meaning
they requested להחריבו, leachrivo, to destroy it, to destroy it. Okay. They
wanted to destroy the מקדש Mikdash because, you know, there was this
constant fight between the Samaritans and the Jews and who were, you
know, who had the real claim. ונתנו להם venatnu lahem or ונתן
להם רשות, venatan lahem reshut, this is another גרסא. girsa. And he
said fine, you're right. Basically as the מהרש״א Maharsha explains, claims- claims-
clearly from the story, they basically said the Jews are rebelling against
you, they reject you, they worship their God, not, you know, not
the Greek gods, and he believed them, and he said and he
passed an edict to destroy the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. This Alexander
the Great is like what, 300 BCE about? Somewhere thereabouts. Okay. All
right. באו והודיעו לשמעון הצדיק. bo vehodi'u leShimon HaTzadik. They told שמעון
הצדיק. Shimon HaTzadik. מה עשה? ma asa? לבש בגדי כהונה ונתעטף בבגדי
כהונה. lavash bigdei kehuna venitattef bebigdei kehuna. He put on his בגדי
כהונה, wrapped himself in his בגדי כהונה. מיקירי ישראל עמו, miyakkirei Yisrael
immo, and the honored, you know, honored people from the community came
with him. We had that phrase before, מיקירי ירושלים, miyakkirei Yerushalayim, what
would accompany the sending over of the goat. Okay, so he was
with very, you know, high-ranking people from the Jewish people. ואבוקות של
אור בידיהם. ve'avukot shel ur beyadeihem. And they were- they were carrying
these torches. וכל הלילה הללו הולכין מצד זה והללו הולכין מצד זה.
vechol halaila hallu holchin mitzad zeh vehallu holchin mitzad zeh. The whole
night they walked to wherever Alexander the Great was encamped, you know,
and
half on one side of
שמעון, Shimon, the
other half of the people on the other side carrying torches, this
very, you know, honorable procession and, you know, noteworthy procession.
עד שעלה עמוד השחר, ad she'ala amud hashachar, until the morning star
rose.
And they walked entire- through the entire night
until the morning star came- came up. וכיון שעלה עמוד השחר, vekivan
she'ala amud hashachar, once the morning star rose, אמר להם, amar lahem,
he said to them, presumably the Samaritans, now we're back to Alexander,
presumably they then arrive to where he was, and Alexander turned to
the Samaritans and said to them, מי הללו? mi hallu? Who are
these people that are coming now in this whole big procession? אמרו
לו, amru lo, so the כותים kutim said to him, יהודים שמרדו
בך. Yehudim shemardu becha. It's the Jews that have rebelled against you.
כיון שהגיע לאנטיפטריס, keivan shehiggi'a le'Antipatris, once they got to אנטיפטריס, Antipatris,
how do they translate that? Does anybody have the- does anybody have
the- is it a place name or
does anybody have a Greek- nobody has there the- the what do
you call it? Yeah, I don't know, let's take a look here,
let's see what our friend שטיינזלץ Steinzaltz says about this. אנטיפרס. Antipartis.
The city near ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was founded by Herod, okay,
next to Rosh Ha-Ayin springs. Alright, so it was a city. Okay,
I don't know, whatever, maybe they were both coming to that city,
I don't know. When they came to אנטיפרס, Antipartis, זרחה חמה, zarchah
chamah, it was no longer the morning, it was no longer the
morning star, now it was actually sunrise. ופגעו זה בזה, upagu zeh
bazeh, they encountered one another. כיון שראה לשמעון הצדיק, kivan she'ra'ah l'Shimon
HaTzadik, now once Alexander saw שמעון הצדיק, Shimon HaTzadik, ירד ממרכבתו, yarad
mimerkavto, he got down from his chariot והשתחוה לפניו v'hishtachaveh lefanav and
he prostrated himself before him. Alexander prostrated in front of שמעון. Shimon.
אמרו לו, amru lo, they, presumably the Samaritans or his retinue, said
to him: מלך גדול כמותך ישתחוה ליהודי זה? melech gadol kemotcha yishtachaveh
l'Yehudi zeh? A great king like you will bow down to this
Jew? A Jew is probably said with a sneer. אמר להם, amar
lahem, he said to them: דמות דיוקנו של זה, demut deyukno shel
zeh, the appearance of this person's face. דיוקן deyukan is really the
Greek icon, okay. The appearance of the icon of the image of
this man מנצח לפני בבית מלחמתי. menatzeach lefanai beveis milchamti. So I
just want to see what they said here. The image of this
man's face, okay, is he is victorious before me when I go
out to battle. So meaning when I go out to battle and
I win all those battles, and Alexander conquered the entire civilized world,
right, I see up in the heavens an image of this man's
face. So clearly he's a very holy man, you know, and it's
because of his merit maybe I've been so victorious. So that's why
I prostrate myself. And so now obviously the whole thing is about
to turn around. אמר להם, amar lahem, so he said to the
Samaritans, למה באתם? lamma batem? I'm sorry, he said to שמעון Shimon
and his retinue: Why have you come? אמרו, amru, so they said,
אמר, amar, so אמרו, amru, they said: אפשר בית שמתפללים בו עליך
ועל מלכותך? efshar bayit shemitpallelim bo alecha v'al malchutecha? We've come, dear
king, for your honor. Is it possible that a temple in which
we pray for you and for the sake of your kingdom, שלא
יחרב, shelo yecharev, that it should not be destroyed? We make prayers
for your welfare. יתעוך עובדי כוכבים להחריבו. yata'ucha ovdei kochavim lehachrivo. These
idolaters are going to come, it's funny they say idolaters as a
sneer, the same way they presumably say Jew as a sneer. I
don't think idolaters was a sneer for Alexander, but okay. Anyway, these
people will come and they want to destroy it, this house that
we pray for for your benefit? אמר להם, amar lahem, he said
to them: מי אלו? mi ellu? So who are those, these people?
So you know, maybe he didn't realize what their affiliation was when
they were sort of telling him to destroy the בית המקדש. Beit
Hamikdash, So אמרו לו: amru lo: כותיים הללו שעומדים לפניך. Kutim hallalu
she'omdim lefanecha. Who are these people? I'm sorry, they maybe just spoke
generically, it's sort of like a whole פורים Purim Esther song, you
know, מי הוא זה ואיזה הוא, mi hu zeh v'eizeh hu, right?
How are you going to let people come persuade you? Who are
the people? No, those are the Samaritans, שעומדים לפניך, she'omdim lefanecha, they're
standing right here in front of you. Right? המן Haman is... they
המן Haman it's, right? It really invokes that whole thing. So who
is this that's trying to destroy this מקדש Mikdash. that's for me
and my מלכות? malchut? It's these Samaritans. אמר להם, amar lahem, he
said to them, to שמעון Shimon and his retinue: הרי הם מסורים
בידכם. harei hem mesurim beyadechem. Fine, you know, exactly, it's really a
פורים Purim story, right? Okay, go hang them. Fine, go hang them.
So they're given over to your hands. With the added detail that
Alexander the Great's entire empire was due to the merit of שמעון
הצדיק. Shimon HaTzadik. Exactly, all of his wars were won, right, and
Hellenism is the merit of the rabbi. Right. By the way, I
was just checking here, the original גרסא girsa is not עובדי כוכבים
ovdei kochavim but גויים להחריבו. goyim lehachrivo. Because obviously they would not
be denigrating them by calling them idolaters, but they did call them
גויים, goyim, the same way the Samaritans called the others Jews, which
means that they thought of themselves very much as separate nations. It's
important to think about, you know, and about in terms of the
גמרות Gemaras that ask whether Samaritans are really halachically Jewish or not.
You know, here clearly they are nations at war with one another,
not literal war but whatever. Why is the term יהודי, Yehudi, isn't
that unusual? No, that you already get in the מגילה, Megillah, that
the land they were living in from the time of עזרא ונחמיה
Ezra v'Nechemya was called יהוד, Yehud, you know, that was the, so
this is when יהודי Yehudi becomes the term. So, okay, so they're
given over to you. So מיד, miyad, immediately, נקבום בעקביהם, nekavum be'ikveihem,
and
this is not going to be so pleasant, especially with שמעון הצדיק
Shimon HaTzadik at the head, they pierced them in their ankles,
ותלאום, utla'um, there's the hanging, okay, again invoking the hanging of בני
המן. bnei Haman. One, they hung them, they suspended them בזנבות סוסיהם,
bezinvos sauseihem, with the tails of their horses. So basically they string
them up through holes that they made in their ankles to the
tails of horses. והיו מגררין אותן על הקוצים ועל הברקנים, vehayu megarrin
osan al hakotzim ve-al habirkanim, and they would basically have the horses
run over thorns and thistles and rocks and pull them along, being
pulled by
wild horses. "couldn't pull me away," you know that? That is a
torture that they would do. They would tie people up to horses
and have the horses run and drag them along, and here they're
dragging them along over these rocks. Okay, עד שהגיעו להר גריזים ad
shehiggiu le-har Gerizim
until they came to הר גריזים Har Gerizim which was their temple.
כיוון שהגיעו להר גריזים, keivan shehiggiu le-har Gerizim,
once they came to הר גריזים, Har Gerizim, not only was it
did they punish these people that tried to destroy the בית המקדש,
Beit Hamikdash. but חרשוה וזרעוה, charashua u-zera'ua,
they plowed it over and they planted it. They basically destroyed it
and converted it into a field, the whole הר גריזים. Har Gerizim.
They destroyed the temple, the temple of the or the holy places,
whether it was a temple, the holy places of the
Samaritans. כרשינין, karshinin, leeks they planted there, כדרך שביקשו לעשות לבית אלוהינו.
kederech shebikshu la'asos leveit elokeinu. They did to them just what they
wanted to do to us, ונהפוך הוא. venahafoch hu. ואותו היום עשאוהו
יום טוב, ve'oto hayom asa'uhu yom tov, and that day was made
into a יום טוב. Yom Tov. Missed that. Okay, that was pretty
powerful. So, by the way, it's also an interesting question because I
think reading stories of Jewish power and Jewish power against enemies is
disturbing for us because classically we're the ones that are oppressed and
afflicted and it's always the bad guys and the non-Jews that are
using their power against us. So I think here this story has
absolutely no problem with it. They got back what was coming to
them in the way the פורים Purim story as well, ויעשו היהודים
בשונאיהם כרצונם. vaya'asu hayehudim besoneihem kirtzonam. I didn't quote that correctly. Anyway,
but that's the point. איבעית אימא, Iba'is eima, but anyway, that was
a wonderful story. So you see he wore בגדי כהונה outside the
בית המקדש. איבעית אימא, Iba'is eima, ראויים לבגדי כהונה, re'uyim levigdei kehuna,
either
it doesn't mean they were literally בגדי כהונה, maybe they were fit
for בגדי כהונה, they hadn't been sanctified yet, but they looked like
בגדי כהונה and that's why he wanted to wear them. ואיבעית אימא,
Ve-iba'is eima, and if you want, עת לעשות לה' הפרו תורתך. es
la'asos la-Shem heferu Torasecha. You know, there are times you have to
break הלכה Halacha for this obviously not huge national issue. Okay, that
was a very powerful story. Now we get on to the actual
passing of the ספר תורה Sefer Torah and reading it. We haven't
concluded whether, no, we had a ברייתא that explicitly said it's ניתנו
ההנאות nitnu ha-hanos at least inside the temple environs, not in the
מדינה, medina, that's a different issue. חזן הכנסת, that was definitely the
conclusion. חזן הכנסת נוטל ספר תורה. chazzan haknesses notel sefer torah. So
you passed it to the חזן, the חזן to the head of
the כנסת, Knesset, to the סגן. sgan. שמע מינה חולקין כבוד לתלמיד
במקום הרב. shema mina cholkin kavod letalmid bimkom harav. It sounds like
you are doing this to give honor to all of these people,
to the head of the שול, shul. to the סגן. sgan. But
why are you giving... so that's a question. Do you give honor
to a less... to a student in the place of his רבי?
These are all lower on the food chain than the כהן גדול.
Kohen Gadol, So maybe it's... maybe
we shouldn't be showing them honor in the presence of the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol. maybe that's a denigration to the honor of the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Does this show that you do that, you
show honor to a student in the presence of the רבי? So
the גמרא says, אמר אביי כולם משום כבודו של כהן גדול הן.
amar Abaye kulam mishum kevodo shel Kohen Gadol hen. No, you missed
the point. We're not giving it to the head of the שול
and from him to the סגן sgan to honor the head of
the שול. We're doing this procession to show the honor of the
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol to show this whole leading up to the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol So it's not honoring them, it's having them
involved in a way of giving honor to the כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol Okay. וכהן גדול עומד, ve-Kohen Gadol omed, and the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol receives it standing and he read from it or stands
literally and reads from it. So עומד, omed, מכלל דמעיקרא יושב? miklal
demayikra yoshev? It sounds like he was sitting, because it says the
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol stands and receives it. Okay,
you could have read it "was standing," but it reads "stands," so
it sounds like he was sitting. ותנן? u-tenan? Don't we teach? אין
ישיבה בעזרה אלא למלכי בית דוד בלבד. ein yeshiva ba-azarah ella lemalkhei
beit David bilvad. The only people that can sit in the עזרה...
azarah... so they're assuming this reading of the תורה Torah. is right
where he was doing the
disemboweling of the קרבנות that we just spoke about, it's taking place
in the temple courtyard. How can you sit in the temple courtyard?
Only the kings of דוד David can. שנאמר, shenemar, the verse says,
ויבא המלך דוד וישב לפני ה', vayavo hamelech David vayeshev lifnei Hashem,
and that's seen as a special allowance for King דוד David and
his descendants. So how could you be doing this in the temple
courtyard, be sitting? So כדאמר רב חסדא, kedamar Rav Chisda, like רב
חסדא Rav Chisda says, בעזרת נשים, be-ezras nashim, they did not do
the reading in the עזרה, azarah, although we didn't mention that the
כהן גדול Gadol? moved anywhere, but now that he's moving to do...
but now that the next step is the reading of the תורה,
Torah. he leaves the עזרה azarah and he goes to the עזרת
נשים ezrat nashim to do it there, which actually could be also
a much more public space, the sense of again we've discussed before
women could go into the
עזרה azarah but obviously it was generally seen as a male space,
עזרת נשים ezrat nashim was much more seen as a mixed space
and it was very large, so the קריאת התורה according to this,
I mean the גמרא doesn't say this, but is now taking place
in a way that is much more public and actually is going
to be alluded to in the next statement, okay.
He went there, he sat
down, right, who knows while he was waiting for the I don't
know and then they gave it to him, he stood up to
receive it. Right, part of the, part of the, right, that's important,
right, that's it.
Right. And the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim is neglected. Right. And yet,
the fact that he's reading the תורה Torah there should elevate it.
Right. So but it doesn't, still doesn't make it into the עזרה.
Azara. I mean, there's more latitude there, but it's true.
I mean, the irony of it is too much, which was to
the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim and he's over there.
Right,
right. Okay. Where does the גמרא say that you move to the
עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim in order to read the תורה? Torah Right,
so to put it in a little, right, translate that word into
a contemporary context. Okay. והיכא איתמר דרב חסדא? Vehaycha itmar deRav Chisda?
So where was רב חסדא Rav Chisda said? אהא, Aha, on the
following. Now this text we're going to read the next few lines
is a little problematic, so there are a lot of changes of
the version, so we're taking out the word מתיבי. Meitevei. On the
following, אהא דתניא, Aha detanya, that's what we taught in the בריתא.
Baraita. היכן קורין בו בעזרה? Heichan korin bo ba'Azara? היכן קורין בו?
Heichan korin bo?
Where would they read from it? Now this might be referring specifically
on יום כיפור, some say a generic question whenever they had to
read, you know, do a reading in the מקדש, where would they
read? Of course, when else did they do a reading in the
מקדש other than הקהל? Hakhel? But okay, where would they read from
it? בעזרה, Ba'Azara, in the עזרה. Azara. So there's one opinion yes,
literally in the עזרה. Azara. רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר: Rabbi Elazar
ben Yaakov omer: בהר הבית. BeHar HaBayit. No, not in the עזרה,
Azara, not even the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, some other place on
the Temple Mount. שנאמר, Shene'emar, outside the מקדש completely. שנאמר: Shene'emar: ויקרא
בו לפני הרחוב אשר לפני שער המים. Vayikra bo lifnei ha'rechov asher
lifnei sha'ar hamayim. So this is in נחמיה Nechemia where they had
a big public reading of the תורה. It says it was by
the way, it says it was on the seventh month which is
תשרי, Tishrei, it might have been ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. Okay, but
it's right around this time of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and יום
כיפור. And it says they had this big public reading, it sounds
like הקהל. Hakhel. It says הנשים והנשים והטף, HaNashim vehaNashim vehaTaph, everybody
was there. And they had a big public reading of the תורה.
Okay. And where did this take place? It says they read לפני
הרחוב Lifnei ha'rechov by the street, by the, you know, street as
like a major thoroughfare, like maybe even like, you know, a square.
אשר לפני שער המים, Asher lifnei sha'ar hamayim, which is by the
gate of the water, which is outside of the מקדש on a
major street. So basically it would be on הר הבית Har HaBayit
but out of the מקדש and it would be in this huge
public setting. And by the way, I think the sort of the
implied parallel between the reading that was done then and the reading
that's done here and the reading to all the people and so
on and the timing is roughly the same. And that's where it
would be outside of the מקדש completely. ואמר רב חסדא: Ve'amar Rav
Chisda: and רב חסדא Rav Chisda says: בעזרת נשים. Be'Ezrat Nashim. Okay,
now is רב חסדא Rav Chisda clarifying when the first opinion says
בעזרה Ba'Azara it means בעזרת נשים? Be'Ezrat Nashim? Is he clarifying that
when רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov says בהר הבית
BeHar HaBayit he doesn't mean anywhere in הר הבית, Har HaBayit, he
means בעזרת נשים? Be'Ezrat Nashim? Not exactly clear. Okay, but anyway you
have three opinions being said here, maybe they conflate to two: עזרה,
Azara, הר הבית, Har HaBayit, and עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. Okay. ויברך
עזרא. Vayevarech Ezra. Now he's quoting these פסוקים let's look at them.
ויברך עזרא את ה' האלוהים הגדול. Vayevarech Ezra et Hashem haElokim hagadol.
עזרא Ezra blessed God, the great God. Okay, this was again in
this context of the reading of the תורה. מאי גדול? Mai gadol?
What does it mean great? You know why is it pointing that
out or another way of framing it which is even better is
דמאי גדלו. Demai gidlo. There's another version of this. In what way
did עזרא Ezra glorify or exalt God? Okay. So אמר רב יוסף
אמר רב: Amar Rav Yosef amar Rav: שגדלו בשם המפורש, Shegidlo beShem
HaMeforash, by enunciating God's, you know, ineffable name. So in this context
he said, you know, he spoke השם Hashem and again the whole
idea of the כהן גדול saying God's name, you know, obviously implicit
parallels that are being drawn. Okay.
How does that liturgically relate to the קדיש, Kaddish, in other words,
what's גדול?
Uh that I don't know if we're making that comparison but we
are making I'm saying, yeah, I understand, it's true. קדיש Kaddish is
יתגדל ויתקדש שמיה רבא, Yitgadal veyitkadash shemeh raba, make His name great.
That is a good point. But I think the more immediate parallel
is the כהן גדול saying the שם המפורש. Shem HaMeforash. That's all,
okay. רב גידל אמר: Rav Giddel amar: Now רב גידל Rav Giddel
says, now again in one version it's בברכה, Bivrakha, but you know
with a ברכה Berakha he blessed God and then quoting the פסוק.
Pasuk. What's the פסוק Pasuk that he glorified God? ברוך ה' אלוהי
ישראל מן העולם ועד העולם. Baruch Hashem Elokei Yisrael min ha'olam ve'ad
ha'olam. Okay, this is from דברי הימים. Divrei HaYamim. There's a very
similar פסוק Pasuk in נחמיה Nechemia if you go ahead and look
in this story. It's interesting that it shifted to the פסוק Pasuk
in דברי הימים, Divrei HaYamim, but this is what he did, he
blessed God, he didn't say God's ineffable name, he blessed God, ברוך
השם. Baruch Hashem. אמר ליה אביי: Amar lei Abaye: By the way,
evokes also what we just spoke about about after the reading of
the תורה the ברכות. And תוספות ישנים said the whole purpose or
the main purpose of the reading of the תורה was to allow
for these ברכות. אמר ליה אביי לרב דימי: Amar lei Abaye leRav
Dimi: So again is it רב דימי, Rav Dimi, some take out
the words רב דימי. Rav Dimi. Anyway, אביי Abaye said: ודילמא שגדלו
בשם המפורש? Vedilma shegidlo beShem HaMeforash? Why do you say it means
they made a ברכה? Berakha? Maybe it means they said God's name?
I don't know and why do you say God's name? Maybe it
means they made a ברכה? Berakha? Anyway, אמר ליה: Amar lei: No,
I don't believe they could have, they would have said God's name.
אין אומרים שם המפורש בגבולין. Ein omrim Shem HaMeforash bigvulin. You don't
say God's name out in the גבולין Gvulin in the like in
the, you know, larger
outside of the מקדש. So even if it's on הר הבית, Har
HaBayit, if we're saying that this takes place not In the עזרה
*azara* proper, you would not be saying שם המפורש *shem hameforash*. So
לא *lo*, do you not דכתיב ויעמוד עזרא הסופר על מגדל עץ
אשר עשו *d'chtiv vaya'amod Ezra hasofer al migdal etz asher asu* לדבר
*l'davar*? He stood on a, he stood on a platform, again sounds
like הקהל *Hakhel*. ואמר רב גידל שגדלו בשם המפורש *v'amar Rav Gidel
she'gidlo b'shem hameforash*, and that he glorified him with God's great name,
so you see they did say God's great name. So it says
הוראת שעה היא *hora'at sha'ah hi*, that was a special exception. Now
this is a very confusing גמרא *Gemara*. We're talking about what did
עזרא *Ezra* do? And it says, oh, I don't want to say
he used God's name. Oh, but doesn't רב גידל *Rav Gidel* say
he used God's name? Fine, that was an exception. But that's exactly
what we're talking about, so what he did at this moment of
the reading of the תורה *Torah* and so on. So some want,
and anyway, where do you get that from this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
about standing on a platform? So some want to say that actually
what the גמרא *Gemara* quotes is the next פסוק *pasuk*, otherwise there's
no transition. And if you look, here's the next פסוק *pasuk*: ויצעקו
אל ה' א-להים בקול גדול b'kol gadol *vayitz'aku el Hashem Elokim b'kol
gadol*. They called out to God in a great name, so again
you have the word גדול *gadol*. So some say that that was
the verse we quoted. What did they call out in a great
name? They called out using God's שם המפורש *shem hameforash*, but that
is an event that is not... it's a later event, not the
event of the reading of the תורה *Torah* of עזרא הסופר *Ezra
hasofer*. So according to this, it says this one opinion is they
did not during this reading that עזרא הסופר *Ezra hasofer* did, they
did not say God's name. You don't say God's name, his שם
המפורש *shem hameforash* outside the מקדש *Mikdash*. What about a פרק *perek*
later where it says they called out to God in a great
call? And we say that means they used God's name? Oh, that
that happened a פרק *perek* later, that was a special exception. But
that's not what happened here. And now we transition to that story,
and this is a very famous אגדתא Aggadeta *agadata* of what that
calling out to God was, which is like a few months after
this event of the reading of the תורה *Torah*. ויצעקו אל ה'
א-להים בקול גדול *vayitz'aku el Hashem Elokim b'kol gadol*. מאי אמור *mai
amor*? What did they say? So we've already possibly said they used
God's great name. What were they calling out about? So אמר רב
ואיתימא רבי יוחנן *amar
Rav v'aitima Rabbi Yochanan*, בייא בייא *baia baia*, like which is please,
please. היינו האי דאחריביה למקדשא *hainu hai d'achreiveih l'mikdasha*,
this is what caused the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash* to be destroyed,
meaning as we're going to see, they are praying to eradicate the
desire for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah, *avoda zara*. Now it's quite fascinating
because if you read these פסוקים *psukim* in נחמיה *Nechemiah*, you will
see that it is a bemoaning the fact that the people have
always sinned and the temple was destroyed because of the sins, but
never mentioned there is a hint of the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
*avoda zara*. It talks about sinning, but it suggests more like moral
sins, other types of sins, there's not a hint of the עבודה
זרה *avoda zara*. But חז"ל *Chazal* are taking this story which is
about them bemoaning the fact of their history of sinning and God
punishing them, and framing it as that they were praying to get
rid of the desire for עבודה זרה *avoda zara*. So בייא בייא
*baia baia*, please, please. היינו האי דאחריביה למקדשא *hainu hai d'achreiveih l'mikdasha*,
it was this עבודה זרה *avoda zara* that led to the destruction
of the temple. וקלייה להיכלא *v'kalyeih l'heichala*, caused the היכל *heichal* to
burn. וקטלינהו לכולהו צדיקי *v'katlin'hu l'chuleihu tzadiki*, caused all the righteous to
be murdered. ואגלינהו לישראל מארעהון *v'aglin'hu l'Yisrael me'arhon*, caused the Jewish people
to be exiled from their land. ועדיין מרקד ביננא *v'adayin merakid beinana*,
and it's still dancing among us. There's still this desire for עבודה
זרה *avoda zara*. How are we going to survive with this new
מקדש *Mikdash* given that we still have this desire that will lead
us astray like the past, which as I said, by the way,
is a theme that's there in the פסוקים *psukim* about acknowledging how
all the sins in the past led to the destruction, but the
גמרא *Gemara* is very much making it about עבודה זרה *avoda zara*.
What are we going to do so it won't happen again? כלום
יהבתה לן אלא לקבולי בה אגרא *klum yehavtah lan
ela l'kabuli bah agra*, the only reason that you gave us this
desire for idolatry was that we should receive reward when we resisted
it. So you know what? לא איהי בעינן ולא אגרא *lo ihi
ba'inan v'lo agra*. We don't want it and we don't want the
reward. It's too dangerous, which evokes the beginning of ברכות *Berachot* where
it says יסורין *yisurin*, if you get people that are afflicted
with
travails and suffering, that it says oh well that's יסורין של אהבה
*yisurin shel ahava* that you should get reward for enduring the suffering.
So it says לא הן ולא שכרן *lo hen v'lo s'charan* and
I'll do without them and without the reward.
Forget it, we don't want this
יצר דעבודה זרה *yetzer d'avoda zara*. ולא אגרא בה נפלה פתקא מרקיעא
*v'lo agra bah naflah pitka merakia*, a piece of paper fell out
from heaven, a little קוויטל *kvittel* it's going the opposite direction. דהוה
כתיב בה אמת Emet. *d'hava k'tiv bah emet*, and was written אמת
*emet*, which means what you said is true. You're right, you made
a legitimate claim. אמר רב חנינא *amar Rav Chanina*, שמע מינה *shma
mina*, we can see from this חותמו של הקדוש ברוך הוא אמת
*chotamo shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu emet*, God's sign is אמת *emet*, right?
Very important point which is going to be a theme that's going
to connect to the next אגדתא *agadata* which we'll get to tomorrow
about this sense of truth as a central part of God's identity.
So you're speaking truth. יתיבו בתעניתא תלתא יומי ותלתא לילוותא *yativei b'ta'anita
tlata yomei v'tlata leilvatha*, they sat three days in a fast and
three nights. מסרוהו ניהליהו *masruhu nihaleihu*, and it was given over to
them, the יצר דעבודה זרה *yetzer d'avoda zara* in some embodied
form. נפק אתא כגוריא דנורא מבית קדשי הקדשים and it came out
like a lion of fire emerged from the Holy of Holies. אמר
להו נביא לישראל amar lehu Navi l'Yisroel and the Navi which we're
going to say means Zechariah said to the Jewish people when this
was happening, they saw this fire coming out, so
היינו יצרא דעבודה זרה hainu yitzra d'avoda zara that's lion of fire
you just saw leave, that's the desire of Avoda Zara. שנאמר ויאמר
זאת הרשעה shenemar vayomer zos harisha this is in one of the
visions of Zechariah interestingly, it's a vision of such a woman in
a pot, and it says this is the wicked woman and then
they seal a lead cover to the pot. So we're connecting this
to the destroying of the יצר הרע דעבודה זרה yetzer hara d'avoda
zara that that's somehow the embodiment of it. בהדי דתפסוה behadei d'tafsuha
so they grabbed the Yetzer Hara of Avoda Zara, I don't know
if it's, it seems a little bit more embodied than this fire
we just spoke of, lay, they grabbed it. אישמיט בינתא ממהזיה ishmita
bintsa m'mazya a hair fell out of its beard. So again, in
Zechariah it's a woman, but here it's got a beard. So it's,
and it's a lion maybe, I don't know if it's still a
lion or if we've shifted from that. Anyway, a hair fell out
of its beard. ורמא קלא v'rama kala lifted up his voice ואזל
קליה ארבע מאה פרסי v'azal kalei arba me'ah parsa and went four
hundred parsangs. So oh, so just to show you the power of
it, that one hair did this, again, it's obviously something symbolic here,
the משל mashal connects it to Esau, you know, who lifted up
his voice and cried out and wants to connect this all with
Esau, Esau is a hairy person. Okay, so that's interesting. אמרי amri
they said, היכי נעביד heichi na'avid now that we've got hold of
this guy, but he's so strong, what are we going to do
to get rid of him? דילמא חס ושלום מרחמי עליה מן שמיא
dilma chas v'shalom mirachamei alei min shamaya we can't just keep him
captive because maybe they'll have compassion on him from heaven and free
him, this Yetzer Hara of Avoda Zara. It's so fascinating how it's
fully embodied
here. אמר להו נביא amar lehu Navi so the Navi said, שדיוה
בדודא דאברא shadyua biduda d'avra put him in a pot and again
this is from the vision of Zechariah with this woman in a
pot with
a lead cover. וחפיוה לפומיה באברא v'chasyua l'pumei b'avra seal the top
of it, the opening with lead, דאברא משאיב קלא d'avra masha'iv kala
because now you see how strong his voice is. Oh, that's the
other point, right? He's lifting up his voice, they cried out to
God בקול גדול they were ויצעקו בקול גדול v'yizaku b'kol gadol and
God answered them. He's now being זועק בקול גדול zo'ek b'kol gadol
so they don't want God to answer him. So what do they
do? They put him in the lead pot, they cover it with
lead because lead דאברא משאיב קלא d'avra masha'iv kala absorbs sound. שנאמר
ויאמר זאת הרשעה וישלך אותה אל תוך האיפה וישלך את אבן העופרת
אל פיה shenemar vayomer zos harisha vayashlech osa el toch ha'eifa vayashlech
es even ha'oferes el piha they cast her, this woman in this
vision of Zechariah, into the pot
and they put the lead stone on its mouth. Okay, so they
got rid of the Yetzer Hara of Avoda Zara, they trapped it,
they didn't completely destroy it but it's trapped, it's sealed, it's bracketed.
אמרי amri they said, הואיל ועת רצון הוא ho'il v'eis ratzon hu
given that God is answering our request, ניבעי רחמי אגיצרא
דעבירה niba'i rachamei agitzra d'aveira let's also pray to conquer over the
desire for sexual sin. בעו
רחמי ba'u rachamei they prayed to God to destroy the desire of
sex as we'll see, ואימסר בידייהו v'imser b'yadeihu and God also gave
that over to their hands. אמר להו amar lehu so he said
to them, presumably Zechariah said to the people, חזו chazu be careful,
דקטלית ליה להאי d'katlis l'hai if you destroy, kill this desire, the
sexual desire, כליה עלמא kalya alma you'll destroy the world because obviously
the world only exists because of procreation which is driven by sexual
desire. So okay, חבשוה תלתא יומי chavshua tlasa yomei they sort of
kept him bound for three days ובעו ביעתא בר יומא v'bau beisa
bar yoma and then they were looking around to find a fresh
egg בכל ארץ ישראל b'chol Eretz Yisroel לא אישתכח lo ishtakach they
couldn't find a fresh egg. The destruction of sexual desire had led
to even the fact that the eggs which were not fertilized, which
is quite fascinating, so it's not actually about sexual activity but it
was so, you know, that even the natural
biological processes that are connected with sex and procreation were not functioning
and there were no eggs. Clearly you cannot do away with the
need for sexual desire in the world and everything that is associated
with it. So what
happened? אמרי amri היכי
נעביד heichi na'avid what should we do? נקטליה niktlei should we kill
it? כליה עלמא kalya alma we see that the world will be
destroyed. ניבעי רחמי
אפלגא niba'i rachamei afalga let's ask for it to be reduced half,
we shouldn't have as much sexual desire. פלגא ברקיעא לא יהבי palga
b'reki'a lo yahavi so they won't give us half of a request.
You have to all or nothing, I don't know what that's about.
Okay. כחלינהו לעיניה kachlinu l'einei
so what they did is they blinded its eyes, literally means they
put some type of makeup on its eyes, but somehow they blinded
its eyes or they put something in its eyes. ושבקוה v'shavkuha and
they left it alone ואהני v'ahani and at least that helped דלא
מיגרי ביה באינש בקריבותיה d'lo migrei beih b'inish b'krivosyei that people should
not want to have desire with their close relatives. With their with
their siblings or with their or with their relatives. Of course, it
didn't really solve that either, but okay, maybe to some degree. So
that's how they, that's how they solved. It's interesting the whole idea
of eyes, because how, lest you see with your eyes, the פסוק
by by what do you call? By the ציצית, Tzitzit, לא תתורו
אחרי עיניכם, lo taturu acharei eineichem, exactly. So anyway, so I'm sorry,
anyway, so, got to figure out how to stop this thing. Anyway.
Okay, so that's the end of that story with that, with getting
rid of the יצר הרע, Yetzer Hara, which is tied up to
the ויזעקו, Vayizaku,
and we will pick up with that tomorrow, but I do want
to say it's too last minute, this idea, I want to just
leave you thinking about something which we'll pick up with tomorrow. This
idea of getting rid of the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara of עבודה
זרה, on the one hand, right, this in the Second Temple period,
late in the Second Temple period, just in the larger world, idolatry
was on the wane, so it might be connected historically to that.
But why is it associated with something leaving the Holy of Holies?
Why, what is that about? That's where the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara
of עבודה זרה is? And I so we're going to talk pick
up with that tomorrow, and then the next אגדתא as well will
echo will tie into this whole idea of God's seal being אמת.
So come back first thing tomorrow, very exciting, bye-bye.